All right.
In this lecture we're going to cover
a Kubernetes architecture.
Just a high level of it.
There's a lot to unpack on this one.
So, don't worry if you if you don't
understand everything at first, go ahead
and use your friendly, ChatGPT or Gemini
to help you understand even more details.
The goal of this is to give
you kind of a high level understanding
of the architecture and the different
terminology that we're seen.
So at a very high level,
the easiest way to think of Kubernetes is,
having a master and a data or a worker.
Right.
So I've got my master node,
which or master nodes
if you want to be high availability,
which is your control plane.
And this is where all the scheduling
of all containers,
and all that orchestration
that needs to happens
can happen in the control plane
or the master.
Right
where I've got a cloud controller manager,
which could be optional,
which can, spin up instances for you.
I've got an API server, I've got a
scheduler, a controller manager,
and I've got a key value store there where
I'm storing state of,
individual nodes,
that worker nodes and even container
information, can go in there.
Then I've got the worker nodes,
and this should be a primarily,
large number of your individual nodes
that you have running in your cluster,
each node,
if it called a data plane, it's really,
execution playing for no better word.
But each one of those worker nodes
will have a cube proxy
for that whole node,
and then it will spin up a cubelet there,
which is an agent there
that will, create things called pods,
which we'll talk about in a little bit.
And inside the pod
is where you're running containers.
Right.
And it can use one of the things
about Kubernetes that you're going to,
learn about is it's, it's
configurability over a convention.
So it gives me a lot of flexibility.
And because of all that flexibility,
it can be sometimes difficult to
set up and manage.
But you can fine tune, Kubernetes,
deployments
for your specific needs that you have.
So just remember that,
that flexibility comes
with high configurability
or high level components.
We've already kind of talked about it
in the control plane.
On the master node,
I've got a centralized rest
API that served up to the API server.
I've got etcd, which is my distributed
key value store for cluster state,
and the individual nodes
will keep track of everything there.
Kube scheduler,
which is assigning pods to specific nodes.
Remember
a pod is where a container actually, runs.
And then I've got kube control manager,
which is running all the controllers
and reconciling the actual state versus
the desired state.
So how do I get my nodes, my worker
nodes, and the pods
all spun up and managed there?
And then I've got a cloud controller node
which can integrate with cloud APIs
if I want to spin up
instances in the cloud.
And this is kind of a,
I'm not going to call it
a gateway,
but it's a controller, for the cloud.
So and you can have multiple different
cloud, manager controller types,
so I can control both private
cloud and public cloud with that.
On the
worker nodes, also known
as the data plane.
I really don't like this name,
because it doesn't
really do anything with data at all.
But the concept here is that,
I got my worker node.
I've got two agents running one.
It is a proxy server,
and it's, forwarding,
and handling node balancing
and at the node level
and I've got my kubelet,
which is like a little, controller
that's running on the node,
to spin up pods
and make sure containers are running
and reporting their status, back.
And then I've got my container runtime,
which is running,
the, those containers in those pods.
And like I mentioned before,
it can handle,
all the different container runtimes.
There's not just Docker d out there.
There's container D and creo.
So if we look at
the control plane flow
on how everything works,
you can see that, we're using,
kube controller, I can the online
where I can apply some kind of a change
that's going to go to the cube API server,
which is my API interface.
It can update state in etcd.
And then my kube scheduler is going to get
called with the desired state
that I want things in.
It will talk to the controller manager
and find,
where the controller manager manages
all the worker nodes
and will, send off to the worker nodes,
what its desired, state is.
And then when the worker no gets all done,
getting to the desired state,
it sits back the actual state,
which hopefully matches the reconciled
or the desired state.
If it does not, it will try another pod
or spin up another pod as necessary
on a different worker node.
Key. Really simple.
Kube controller is the main interface,
similar to Docker.
Docker has
Docker is the interface with Kubernetes.
It's kube controller qb ctl.
And this is, this is talking directly
to the API server.
Right?
The API server is writing
all the desired state into etcd,
which is a key value store.
And we've already talked
about scheduling pods on to nodes.
And then the controller manager
is trying to reconcile
the desired state against,
the actual state.
That's its main job.
Okay.
If I look down at the worker node
when, when I'm asking to do things
down on the worker node,
it all comes through the controller.
Manager controller from the,
master nodes.
Right?
It's that I mean, that's
where things happen.
They don't happen, directly,
to, an individual, worker node
except going through the,
controller node, the master.
Right.
So you can see that it's going to spin up
a container runtime, a pod, it's
going to set up the proxy so that I know,
what services are running inside,
that pod or that container.
And then it's also going
to, update any iptables
as necessary depending on the network,
configuration that you have.
So it's very simple.
If I've got the, the,
kubelet there
that's handling spinning up the nodes
and I've got the proxy that's handling
all the traffic between the nodes,
I have
specifically the Kennedy containers.
So the worker node,
I've got pod assignment pod
lifecycle, health and status.
This is really important
for observability,
which we will be talking about
as observability in future lectures.
Right. And then service networking.
This is through the cube proxy.
And the flexibility
that I have with Kubernetes.
It can use that same kube proxy to,
handle several different types
of configuration,
technology and design patterns
that are out there.
All right.
So back to the core,
objects and key concepts here.
I've got a namespace concept
where I can group multiple pods together
into the same namespace.
And typically these
will all fit inside the same.
Oh no I don't want to say,
micro segmented network, but kind of
but the idea here is that all of the pods,
no, can access each other
in the same namespace.
That's the key concept here.
I got individual pods that are running on
a, worker node,
and, I can have multiple pods
serving up the same, service
that is in this in a namespace.
And this
this is very similar to Docker Swarm.
And then I can have a service has multiple
runtime containers serving serving that.
So load balancing
becomes a key issue here.
And that's all handled by the replica
replica
set controller,
which is the the master node.
All right.
So let's talk about some of these,
key things.
I've got a pod
that's the smallest deployable unit
for container
sharing network. And volumes.
I can have multiple containers
in the same pod.
This is, very this is a concept
that does not exist in Docker.
They kind of said we don't need that
granularity,
but there's some benefits to this in that
I can have a bunch of containers
that are tightly, integrated together.
Maybe they're tightly coupled.
I can decrease the amount of network
traffic going over the network by jamming
more into the same pod.
There's sharing the same network.
They're sharing the same values.
This is a great, a great addition here.
A service, can involve multiple pods,
same container across multiple pods.
This gives me scalability, load balancing.
For the pods, I've got deployment.
Which is, how do I to deploy
these replica sets that, that
match the services?
That configuration maps and secrets
very common,
that we're seeing in, Docker as well.
And then, namespace,
which gives me a virtual cluster partition
so I can create, that
this would be somewhat analogous
to a stack in Docker Swarm.
But it's got even a richer, taxonomy
or vernacular to it.
And then I've got my admin controller,
which is enforcing all of the policies
in the API requests, which,
we we've already talked about.
All right.
Let's talk about networking model
just briefly because there's
a whole lecture on networking.
You can have networks that are very flat
like we've seen in other.
I can have CNI,
plugins that implement several different,
networking,
design patterns.
And then I can also do,
the load balancing with the cube proxy,
right where I get one proxy
and I can, I can hit multiple services.
And with just really simple load
balancing based in there.
So lots of flexibility
on the networking model.
And this configurability
and flexibility gives me a great way of,
enforcing an architectural, decision
that I made.
But it comes with configurability
and complexity.
High availability.
I've already kind of briefly mentioned
how in high available systems, I'll have
multiple, API servers, schedulers,
master nodes basically.
Right.
And I need to be able to coordinate
between those.
Right.
And these are quorum, architecture.
To do that, I can scale horizontally
by adding several worker nodes.
One of the things that we found
with Kubernetes and most of same
with Docker Swarm,
most of these major cluster things is
connectivity is extremely important
between the nodes.
It was built on the cloud for the cloud.
So there's a lot of,
assumptions
that you have, clear connectivity
all the time in some systems,
like, at the edge or systems
in denied, degraded,
intermittent and low latency
or deal environments.
These types of architectures
are fall apart pretty quick.
So you have to come up
with some other options which we will be
talking later.
Architectures.
Again, we've talked about observability
and security.
It's kind of baked in to, Kubernetes.
And I can plug in a lot of third party
tools to help me define and,
not just define, but see what's going on
and, enforce security.
So as I've already mentioned,
Kubernetes does a really good job,
with their architecture
in, decoupling control and data
planes to well-defined APIs.
Also, the scalability
is there, the configurability.
So if you have a certain
architectural design,
that you want to enforce, unlike in
Docker Swarm where you get what you get,
Kubernetes allows me to manipulate
and change
the underlying architecture
by plugging in different, technologies.
So if you need flexibility or you have a,
unique
situation, this is a great way to go.